<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<document xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:ns0="https://open.law/schemas/cache" id="PR43-002" codify:doc="Chickasaw Nation Code">
  <num>PR43-002</num>
  <heading>Amendment to Title 5 of the Chickasaw Nation Code (Manner of Selection of Judges)</heading>
  <meta>
    <stub/>
    <effective>2026-02-20</effective>
    <history>
      <adopted>2026-02-20</adopted>
    </history>
    <citations>
      <citation type="res" url="./adopted/PR43-002.pdf">PR43-002</citation>
    </citations>
  </meta>
  <codify:replace path="5|2|B|5-202.3" codified:doc="Chickasaw Nation Code" codified:path="§5-202.3">
    <section>
      <prefix>Section</prefix>
      <num>5-202.3</num>
      <heading>MANNER OF SELECTION OF JUDGES.</heading>
      <text>Judges shall be appointed by the Supreme Court of the Chickasaw Nation and upon a vacancy occurring in a judicial office in the following manner:</text>
      <para>
        <num>1.</num>
        <text>Within thirty (30) days after a vacancy occurs the Supreme Court Clerk shall cause a notice of the vacancy stating the minimum qualifications, the date the application period will close, and any other pertinent information to be published once in the Chickasaw Times. Copies of the notice may be posted at the office of the Clerk of the Supreme Court, and such other places as directed by the Supreme Court. The notice shall direct that inquiries, nominations and applications be directed to the Court Clerk's office who shall keep a permanent record of responses to such notices. The Supreme Court Clerk may, at the request of the Supreme Court, publish the notice of vacancy in electronic or paper format in any publication or forum deemed appropriate by the Supreme Court including but not limited to bar or judicial journals, employment seeking forums or websites, social media, the Chickasaw Nation's website, or any other publication deemed appropriate by the Supreme Court.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>2.</num>
        <text>The Supreme Court Clerk shall deliver the names and files of all persons nominated or applying for the judicial office to all members of the Supreme Court within five (5) business days of the closing date stated in the notice of vacancy.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>3.</num>
        <text>The Supreme Court shall review the qualifications of the applicants or nominees, and may interview them at the Court's discretion. In making a selection, the Supreme Court shall give preference to those candidates who:</text>
        <para>
          <num>a.</num>
          <text>have more formal education and experience in the legal field.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>b.</num>
          <text>by written or oral examination conducted by the Supreme Court or by interview have shown that they are familiar with the Constitution, Code and Common laws of the Chickasaw Nation.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>c.</num>
          <text>have demonstrated decision making ability.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>4.</num>
        <text>If the nominee for the judicial office is appointed, the nominee shall be sworn into office by the Chief Justice, or the next ranking available Justice of the Supreme Court.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>5.</num>
        <text>If the applicant or nominee is not appointed, the Supreme Court shall either republish the notice and establish a new list of eligible candidates, or reconsider the candidates on the list gathered from the previous notice. The Supreme Court nomination process shall continue until an applicant or nominee is confirmed.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>6.</num>
        <text>Upon the expiration of a judicial term of office, the judicial officer is entitled upon request, filed with the Supreme Court Clerk not less than sixty (60) days prior to the expiration of his term, to be considered for confirmation to a new term.</text>
      </para>
    </section>
  </codify:replace>
</document>
